# RAHUL K JHA

PRINCIPAL SOFTWARE ENGINEER



+91-8290-23-8014



jharahulkumar12@gmail.com



Hyderabad

### **About Me**

With 7+ Years of experience, a passionate backend developer having expertise in developing web applications in multiple programming languages including but not limited to Java, JavaScript & PHP. Interested in Web Security, System Design and Scaling application to handle a large number of concurrent users & possess a good understanding of Data Structures, Object Oriented Design, RDBMS & Distributed Systems

# **Experience**

#### **ACS Solutions (2018 - Current)**

Principal Software Engineer

#### 1. Cannabis Potency Testing web app for a US based client

- Lead a team of 7 developers to build a SAAS application to simplify the cannabis potency testing process from scratch
- Discussed and refined the requirements with the client to develop optimized solution for the required features
- Assisted the ops team in setting up the required infrastructure to host and scale the application for a large number of users in the best possible performance
- Developed automated API test environment using Postman to reduce the application testing time which lead to fast feature rollout for users

Technology: Java, ROR, ReactJS, MySql, Redis

### 2. Research & Analysis Data Management App for a US based client

- Lead a team of 10 developers to build an scale REST API for a research analytics data management application
- Improved API average response time by 150% for web & mobile clients
- Implemented auto scaling feature to tackle sudden surge in user requests
- Add various functionality like caching & load balancing at application & data layer to reduce the server load which in turn saved infrastructure cost and improved user experience
- Added various security enhancements including JWT based authentication & 2FA
- Implemented full text search functionality from scratch to improve the content search results
- Added Single Sign On feature using Azure Active Directory which lead to faster login experience for enterprise users
- Added user activity tracking using GA4 to help in gathering user's application usage behaviour and generated dashboard to pin down the areas of improvement in Web & Mobile client

Technology: NodeJs, ReactJS, MySql, Redis, RabbitMQ, Google BigQuery, ElasticSearch

#### 3. E-Commerce Application for a US based medical organisation

- Added various new features including a fallback payment gateway integration
- Scaled the application to handle 3M visitors per month
- Moved hosting to the cloud from on-premise
- Setup Kubernetes cluster & docker based hosting for automated scaling depending on the number of users & load
- Decreased the page load time to half & implemented various security enhancements

Technology: PHP, JavaScript, MySql, Redis, ElasticSearch

### Meltag Inc (2017 - 2018)

Senior Software Engineer

#### 1. Campaign & Loyalty Management Application

- Developed the Backend API for a Campaign Management Application for Web, Mobile & SMS based interface
- Decreased the Infrastructure cost by 20% by implementing various application and infrastructure level improvements
- Improved API response time by 30% by implementing various code improvements

Technology: Java, VueJS, MySql, Redis, Erlang

#### **Tattvam Media (2015 - 2017)**

Software Engineer

#### 1. Digital Media Marketing Engagement Analytics Application

- Lead a team of 4 developers to build and scale an in-house application from scratch to manage and track digital media marketing conversion rate by pulling in data from various sources like Google Adwords & Facebook Marketing & created a dashboard for actionable insights
- Understood the requirements of marketing team and worked on developing optimised solution
- Setup & manage cloud based hosting environment

Technology: Java, Javascript, MySql, Redis

# **Open Source Contribution**

### **Sentry Integration For Magento**

Added New Feature

 Added a new feature that has let user enable or disable the integration on demand Pull Request Link: <a href="https://github.com/justbetter/magento2-sentry/pull/59">https://github.com/justbetter/magento2-sentry/pull/59</a>

# Hackathon (2019)

#### **Dobby Chat Bot**

A Chat Bot for newly joined employees

Developed a Teams bot that can answer the question regarding the organization's structure, people
& process for newly joined employees. Technology included Python & Google Dialogflow

# **Area of interest**

- Web Security
- REST API Design
- Distributed Computing

# **Education**

2015

RTU Kota

BTech in Computer Science & Engineering

# **Technology & Expertise**

Java	
JavaScript	
PHP	 _
RDBMS	
AWS	
Docker	

### **Web Presense**

**Github** 

https://github.com/t9toqwerty

Website

https://rahulkjha.com

Linkedin

https://www.linkedin.com/in/t9toqwerty/

Stackoverflow

https://stackoverflow.com/users/2668465/